In 1989, Edward Said warned us about the racist and Orientalist perspectives of Thomas Friedman.
Said believed Friedman felt entitled and encouraged as well as authorized to advocate for extreme measures in the region.
Now, since I started writing in English about the Middle East, Palestine, and Israel about 20 years ago,
Friedman's perspectives have been consistently proven wrong.
His analyses are racist, reductive, and contradictory.
And it's disgraceful, but not surprising, that the New York Times continues to publish such garbage.
Edward Said wrote, and I quote,
Friedman belongs very clearly on one side, the side associated with classical anti-Arab and anti-Islamic Orientalism.
What is particularly shady is that Friedman palms off his opinions and those of his sources as uncontested and secure.
Obviously, his sources are more often than not one taxi driver in Egypt out of 100 million who is going to be his undeniable source on all things Arab and Muslim.
As Edward Said writes, the point, of course, is that what Friedman and the Orientalists espouse is a threadbare repertoire of often racist cliches,
all of them bearing the marks of colonial knowledge.
Now, Friedman decided to understand the Middle East through the animal kingdom this week.
Always a great idea, of course, to compare people to animals in a context of genocide and dehumanization.
He's literally parroting Israeli leaders who call Palestinians human animals.
And surprise, surprise, the more noble animals are the U.S. and Netanyahu, respectively a lion and a lemur,
while all the locals are just insects and parasites that should be squished with a bug.
Anyway, so, for instance, Iran, one of the world's oldest civilizations,
is a parasitoid wasp that injects its eggs into live caterpillars,
the caterpillars being Lebanon, Yemen, Syria, and Iraq,
and the wasp's eggs, the Houthis, Hezbollah, Hamas, and Qatab.
Hezbollah, Hamas, by the way, on top of being a parasitoid wasp egg,
is also apparently a trapdoor spider.
Go figure.
And apparently, the old lion that is the U.S. has no counter-strategy that safely and efficiently
kills the wasp without setting fire to the whole jungle, i.e. burn the Middle East down.
It doesn't even make sense.
I mean, why would a lion who lives in the savannah be bothered by a jungle wasp?
Is it because him and the lemur are really friendly?
The lemur eats caterpillars.
Somehow also bothered by the eggs and the parasites.
I don't know.
Sounds like a whole bunch of garbage.
That does make sense.
So there it is, geopolitics, explained to Americans by the New York Times' premier columnist.
We're the king of the animals.
We're burdened by these parasites and insects in the jungle,
and we might just have to burn the entire jungle down.
Literally is the article right there, in a nutshell.
I mean, the mayor of Dearborn, Abdullah, a friend of mine, actually,
someone who I had the pleasure to meet several years ago while he was campaigning and running
back in Dearborn, has been calling out the horrific and racist Wall Street Journal headline
and article titled, Welcome to Dearborn, America's Jihad Kapro.
Now, he rightfully calls it garbage that is reckless, bigoted, and Islamophobic.
He also goes on to say that Dearborn is actually one of the greatest American cities in our nation,
citing that it is the fastest-growing city in Michigan.
It is home to the number one travel destination in Michigan,
which is the Henry Ford Museum in the Greenfield Village.
It's also home of the Ford Motor Company.
It's also sort of the Mecca or, like, the Mecca,
the coffee-food culture capital of Michigan, the Mecca of Michigan,
among the most diverse cities as well in the state.
And Mayor Abdullah also went on to announce that, effective immediately,
Dearborn police will ramp up their presence across all places of worship and major infrastructure
points as a direct result of the racist and inflammatory Wall Street Journal opinion piece
that has led to an alarming increase in bigoted and Islamophobic rhetoric that has been targeting
the city of Dearborn online.
So, between this article from the Wall Street Journal and Thomas Friedman calling the Middle
East a jungle in the New York Times, is it really any wonder why U.S. policy in the region
is devoid of not just empathy and humanity, but facts?
I mean, the fact is, in case you still haven't woken up and smelled the hummus,
they simply do not see Arabs as full humans.
And they're kind of unapologetic about it.
And you know who else agrees with them?
All those Israeli officials who are calling us Palestinians inhuman animals.
Elite political media pundits are losing, and arguably have lost a long time ago,
their sense of basic humanity when publishing this kind of trash.
It's appalling, it's disgraceful, it's obscene, it's offensive, it's dangerous,
but it's not surprising for anyone who has, for example, read Thomas Friedman before.
And just so it's not lost on us, Friedman is describing an entire region as an animal kingdom,
just in the headline, without even reading the piece.
It should be clear what is happening here.
And you know, friends say to me and have for some time,
is there no editor in these sort of, you know, the liberal New York Times,
and like someone to kind of check them or, you know, maybe say something before this gets published?
I mean, there is, but clearly, if you're expecting there to be accountability for this level of
dehumanization, you really shouldn't be holding your breath, because I can tell you firsthand,
this is not just tolerated.
It is encouraged, it is mainstreamed, and it is intentional.
Otherwise, it wouldn't happen over and over and over.
And if this was written about any other people, you better believe that the author would be fired
even before the ink has time to dry on the paper.
So as America gears up for another election,
just remember how deeply entrenched anti-Arab racism and Islamophobia is,
how mainstream it is.
The same right-wing outlets who warn of rising anti-Semitism have no problem
sharing and publishing horrendous Islamophobia and anti-Arab racism.
Imagine the Wall Street Journal headline was written about a predominantly Jewish or Black
community or area in the U.S.
Just imagine what the reaction would have been.
So just to review, Dearborn is a jihad capital, according to the Wall Street Journal,
and according to the New York Times, the Middle East is best understood
through the lens of animals, insects, and the jungle.
And the editor, by the way, across the pond, of the U.K.'s Jewish Chronicle
is also simultaneously suggesting that pro-Palestinian doctors
or doctors who believe in Palestinian humanity should be fired.
So Thomas Friedman can compare all Arabs and Iranians to bugs and insects in his op-ed.
But Greta Thunberg had to apologize to the whole world
because she happened to have an octopus-stuffed animal in a photo.
The only way the New York Times can actually remedy this,
should they care to, is to pull the article, apologize, and fire Tom Friedman.
But it's really that simple.
To call this a dereliction of duty is a gross understatement.
At a time when anti-Arab, anti-Palestinian, and anti-Muslim rhetoric is at an all-time high,
the choice, and it is a choice, to publish this content with this headline
is reckless at best and very malicious at worst.
Let's not forget that a six-year-old Palestinian-American boy
was stabbed dozens of times and killed, and his mom hospitalized.
Let's not forget that three Palestinian-American students were shot
and one of them was left paralyzed.
Are we really to believe that the editors at the New York Times or the Wall Street Journal
simply didn't know better?
Maybe you read Friedman's piece and you're still trying to understand
why Tom and his editors thought it was a good idea to compare human animals in a genocide
in which Palestinians have already been demonized as human animals
by the people who are enacting the genocide against them
and have been ethnically cleansing them for 75 years?
Maybe, maybe, you didn't make it to the end of the piece.
Well, here is the last line.
This is the closing line in the piece that the New York Times ran by Thomas Friedman.
You know, it's not just a sexy slogan to say decolonize the media.
It's actually something that is very necessary in order for us to have a chance
at a more safe and harmonious future.
Media outlets like the Wall Street Journal, the New York Times, CNN, Fox,
and don't get me started on the BBC and Sky News of it all,
but all these outlets that are disseminating incitement to genocide,
dehumanizing narratives, justifying Israel's daily committing of war crimes,
crimes against humanity, collectively punishing Palestinian people,
peddling Israeli propaganda and disinformation and masquerading it as journalism.
This all must be held accountable.
People must be held accountable for this.
Incitement and complicity in genocide are actual crimes.
That last line, though, I just...
...